HMBB, hold my beer, or the slightly less
interesting beta hydroxy beta
methylyrate.
I'm pretty late to the game considering
that there have already been videos of
plenty discussing its effectiveness with
a mixture of opinions. But what if we
looked at 20 plus studies on the topic?
And can we get some more concrete
answers then? Yes, we can. It's not
straightforward, but I will do my best
to give you clear actionable input by
the end. Generally, the idea behind HMBB
is that when you consume it, it reduces
muscle breakdown and increases muscle
protein synthesis. I'll be making
separate content on the specifics of
that. But for now, in a very general
sense, just know that it is primarily
known to reduce breakdown of proteins
within the muscle cells and it has some
effect at raising protein synthesis,
which would theoretically increase
muscle size and potentially muscle
function. So, aside from how it's
supposed to work, do we actually see
evidence that supplementing with HMBB
improves muscle, especially as we get
older? For that, we can lean on two
similar but slightly distinct analyses
of many studies. In these analyses,
researchers searched for all the
randomized control trials that they
could find that compared supplementing
HMBB to people not supplementing. In
this one, 21 trials were included,
including people over 50 years old, men
and women. And when looking at muscle
mass, we have six of the 21 studies on
the left side. Each box is the result of
each study. The more right of the red
vertical line there, the greater the
muscle effect of HMBB supplementation.
That green diamond at the bottom is the
overall effect. All the studies
combined. Clearly, it sits to the right.
Now, we can do something similar for
muscle function because muscle size does
not always translate onetoone with
improved muscle function. And we clearly
see an effect here as well. again
indicated by the diamond with many more
studies included moving to the right and
statistically confirmed. Okay, so to put
it simply, HMBB supplementation leads to
improvements in muscle size and function
in people 50 and older. The thing is
though, does that necessarily make it
worthwhile to supplement with? Well,
that depends on a number of things, some
of which are addressed in the same
analysis. In the study, they performed a
subgroup analysis. Oo, subgroup
analyses. I like those. Which means that
the researchers didn't just look at the
total 2,00 participants, but bucketed
the data into different defined groups.
For example, if people exercised or not,
or by dose or by sex, and so on. Now,
while HMBB has been discussed primarily
because it supposedly prevents muscle
breakdown, which might play in favor of
people getting older and possibly losing
muscle over time as they don't exercise.
It turns out that HMBB is ineffective if
exercise is not paired with it. Beyond
that, when bucketing based on dosing,
dosing matters as well. Studies using
too low of a dose seem to indicate
reduced effectiveness. Most effective
studies use 3 g. Even beyond these two
important points, there is more to
consider. Some weaknesses in the
evidence that may sway if you want to
invest in HMBB or not. Before we touch
on those, there are a combination of
supplements that seem to supercharge
HMBB's effectiveness, both for
exercisers and surprisingly for nonex
exercisers as well. And in fact, there
are other considerations that make a
difference on HMBB's effectiveness. If
you're interested, I'm covering all
those in the extended analysis, which
includes more studies. You also get an
accompanying article along with a whole
library of other analyses in video,
written, and even podcast form. as I
release a regular podcast for the
Physionic Insiders where this is all
kept. Membership as an insider also
comes with all these perks right over
here. So, feast thine eyes. The link to
access everything is in the description.
I'll see you over there. Before we go on
to some of these important nuances, the
summary up to this point is that HMBB
should be dosed at 3 g minimum and
should be paired with exercise if taken
alone. Now, these nuances, these
weaknesses and evidence that I'm
alluding to, come down to A, some mild
statistical imperfections that I won't
bore you with. B, the quality of the
evidence, according to the researchers,
is quite low in some metrics. And C,
there's an issue with comparing against
placeos and regular control groups. In
this context, I'll skip to the quality
of the evidence, which isn't top tier by
any means. For one, the researchers fail
to incorporate studies from an unbiased
database called CL clinical trials. That
database ensures that uh studies that do
not get published for whatever reason
are still required to hand over their
results, good or bad. That would mean
that this analysis may be missing a few
studies that would indicate no effect of
HMBB. The final aspect is the
comparisons used in these trials. So
both meta analyses which mostly agree
with one another even when extending up
to people with sarcopenia. So, age
related muscle loss in your 70s and 80s
and beyond. Use either placeos
or don't give the comparison group
anything. In the purest sense, that's
fine. Well, the placeos are fine, but
considering that we're discussing muscle
growth and function, it would be ideal
to compare against proteins, especially
leucine rich proteins, which is the
amino acid that HMBB comes from,
leucine. There are some studies
comparing leucine to HMBB, but they're
short and or underdose HMBB except for
one which indicated no preference
between HMBB or leucine supplementation.
However, the study was in young
individuals, so not the main population
or goal of interest that we're pursuing
here. In addition, the type of HMBB
might matter because many studies use
calcium HMBB. Yet some reviews indicate
free HMBB may be superior to calcium
bound HMBB as it is more readily
absorbed. All right, that was a lot.
Putting it all together, where does that
leave us? Should we take HMBB or not to
prevent muscle loss like sarcopenia?
Well, it does seem that HMBB is
effective for people 50 and older. We
just don't know if it's uniquely
effective over other muscle promoting
molecules. As it stands, when compared
against placebo, it does seem to have an
effect. That's point number one. Number
two, the evidence more strongly points
to pairing HMBB with exercise,
especially resistance training. So,
consuming 3 g of free HMBB per day, and
resistance training indicates the best
effects. Number three, although we're
discussing effectiveness, none of the
results in these studies indicate
massive effects. Yes, it's effective at
improving muscle and strength, but it
isn't going to turn you into alatenega.
So, is HMBB for you? Comment below if
you'll give it a try. No one will
respond, but that's what all the
YouTubers say, and then they never
engage with the audience. I love that
energy. What I find better than HMBB
because it has excellent evidence behind
it for older folks is creatine. I go
over the evidence right here.
I will respond. I'm not an ass.